The vast majority of Chinese was living under the poverty line.
We could not even make one car or one airplane.
Today, China’s interests encompass the entire world.
If you dare not stand up and defend your own interests, who will stand up for you?
China Now with Zhang Weiwei
I'm open to anything. From the left to the right,
we are open to all communication.
"Democracy", "freedom", "human rights",
the so-called "media control", "Internet control" ...
We can talk about all these. Why not?
I studied politics before I became the translator of our national leaders.
I always say, when you talk about any problems,
your research must stand up to being questioned.
I distinctly feel that our attitude towards
the outside world is much stronger.
He expresses his views in a very gentle and rational way.
I think this is also true for him as a person, which makes him awesome.
Did you write this book and make notes as you travelled?
I had the habit of keeping a diary.
Later, when I was doing my doctoral dissertation,
I reviewed the discussions on "Reform and Opening"
between Chinese leaders and foreign guests.
That was when I developed my own thoughts about
what we call "the China Path" today,
which is a series of practices of China.
I see Qinglin has been standing there for a while.
This is what we discussed about Episode 1 in the production meeting.
The production meeting of the pre-production team?
Yes.
- Oh, you made it into a video?
- We did.
- Are they all your students?
- They are.
- You gave lectures to all of them?
- I did.
I heard all kinds of opinions on Meng Wanzhou's incident.
Some said that she should comply with US law,
and Huawei also said they believed that US
and Canadian laws would make an impartial judgement.
But if you look at the announcement from the Ministry of Foreign Affairs,
it says "release Ms. Meng Wanzhou immediately".
In this incident, Canada itself is not the major player.
We all understand who is behind this.
This is about 5G.
Even if they did this to defeat the 5G giant,
they have taken the stupidest approach.
Personally speaking, I can't stand it when some professors say,
"Oh, we must surrender now. Some core technologies
are not necessary for every country to have."
It's like "Oh, lay down our arms."
Who told you they won't kill when you lay down your arms?
Putting down the arms is your own choice, but killing is their decision.
Only the Eighth Route Army would let the surrenders live.
Yeah, if they want to kill you, they will kill regardless.
Only we treat the captives kindly.
For decades, some may have been
faithful to and looking up to the West,
or "the perfect world on the other shore",
and been feeling happy about it.
Then all of a sudden, they found out that this wasn't the case anymore, which was beyond their acceptance.
They fled away with the thought that you were all wrong.
When you repeatedly see these professors' articles,
it shows that we are very confident, not afraid of
them misleading the public opinion.
China-U.S. trade frictions have lasted for a year.
At first, everyone felt very uncertain.
This time, from Chinese people to the government and to Huawei,
all their reactions greatly raised national pride.
It turns out that Huawei has become the "fear" of another country.
It is particularly necessary to make sense of what happened
because some people have been saying that
China should continue to "hide its light".
But I feel that there is no way we can avoid "showing the light".
How can you hide when you are already standing right there?
It's like "an elephant in the room".
Don't get so excited.
It's not ... The problem is not like "an elephant in the room".
In fact, a problem can be handled in many different ways.
After I get strong, we can join hands and go together ...
towards a higher stage of affluence.
For example, a win-win alliance, is one way.
And we have come all the way with our win-win alliances.
Like Professor Zhang said,
the reason why we really believe in "win-win", not just preaching it,
is that we are able to offer "win-win" solutions.
But I think Prof. Zhang will have to make it clear
where the solution is to this problem.
So, Qinglin had a question for you in the end.
I did.
I will answer that. (laughs)
I look forward to your answer.
China Now with Zhang Weiwei
Different views can be discussed and debated.
We are not at all afraid of competition.
China, be confident.
China Now with Zhang Weiwei
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 微信公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
Hello everyone, welcome to China Now.
We will discuss the latest hot topics together to
learn about China, understand China, and position China!
Standing next to me is our keynote speaker,
Professor Zhang Weiwei, Director of the China Institute of Fudan University.
Welcome!
Thank you!
At the beginning of Reform and Opening [1980s],
Professor Zhang served as a translator for party and
national leaders, including Comrade Deng Xiaoping.
Professor Zhang also visited more than 100
countries and regions in the world.
He arguably has a profound observation of
the development of China and the world.
I really think that horizontal comparison will help us
understand China and the world.
I agree.
There are many young people in the audience today,
and our young friends came with their own questions.
I particularly look forward to having a dialog with them today.
Professor Zhang and I have watched a video
reporting the work status of pre-production team.
The pre-production team is made up of media
professional who are engaged in reporting current affairs.
They have their own observations and reflections on China as well.
Now, I will give the stage to Professor Zhang.
We will get into the first topic of China Now together!
Welcome.
Thank you.
When we get to the Q&A segment,
you can ask me any questions.
There are no restricted zones, or "no taboo" in English.
The questions can be as pointed as you want.
In the video we saw some meaningful questions were raised.
One question is "win-win cooperation", which we always talk about.
Can we continue to go down that road?
Another question is, what was the purpose of
America taking a hostage from Huawei?
There hasn't been any evidence [against Huawei] so far .
Sometimes a bad thing can turn out to be good in a sense.
Most of the young people here can still recall
Yinhe incident in 1993 while some may not remember it.
There were the United States bombing
the Chinese embassy in Belgrade in 1999,
a China-US aircraft collision in the South China Sea in 2001,
attacks during Beijing Olympics torch relay in Paris in 2008,
and this year, abduction of a Huawei executive.
I think these incidents are awakening more and more Chinese people,
and I would even say they are a kind of "coming-of-age
ceremony" for the overall revival of our entire nation.
Because over the years, many of us, especially some
intellectuals, have acted very naively.
They always felt there was an extremely beautiful world
on the other side - the West, America in particular.
But it turns out that this "perfect world" is fictional.
In fact, the Meng Wanzhou incident exposed
too much hypocrisy and hegemony of America.
What happened to the promised market economy,
fair competition, and free trade?
Where is their spirit of contract?
What about democracy and human rights?
All gone.
We can see that in the world's most competitive 5G race,
in terms of the core technologies and the establishment of standards,
Huawei has actually caught up with their competitors,
and even surpassed their competitors in many aspects.
This made them afraid,
and in fear they resorted to restricting competition by foul play.
Fortunately, China has risen.
Our leaders went through the chaos in the
Cultural Revolution; I also experienced part of it.
We know how to deal with rogues.
I believe that this incident will eventually be resolved
under the strong pressure from the Chinese people.
China will also move faster to the center of
the world's political and economic arena.
When Deng Xiaoping talked about "hiding our light",
China's economy was smaller than Russia's.
But today, Russia's economy is about the size of our Guangdong Province.
In other words, we have grown into Yao Ming [7' 6"].
Can we still want to hide behind Pan Changjiang [5' 3"]?
That is very difficult.
Even 30 years ago, when Deng Xiaoping
talked about keeping a low profile,
he was very clear that keeping a low profile was just
a means to end, and the end is to make a difference.
Because today, China's interests encompass the entire world.
If you dare not stand up and defend your own interests,
who will stand up for you?
Moving on to the question of whether cooperation and win-win is possible.
We, the Chinese people, have come all along with true faith in it.
But now the problem is that there is a
leading country that still doesn't believe it.
It only believes that its own interest comes first in the world
and only believes in zero-sum games,
in which only one part can win.
The Chinese people play Go, a game
to form "potential" with strength.
China is now the largest trading partner of more than 130 countries.
This is our strength and our potential.
If a country believes that only itself can take first place in the world,
I think it's necessary for such a country to adapt to the general trend
and come to the road of win-win cooperation.
These are my thoughts on some of your previous questions.
Now when we look back at the past 70 years,
from the founding of the People's Republic of China in 1949,
it has been very difficult.
In 1949, our newly founded republic was caught up with the Korean War.
When Americans hit the doorstep of the Chinese people,
we had no choice but to rise up and fight.
Chairman Mao said, "One strong punch
will save a hundred more."
The Korean War was a battle to establish our international position,
an exchange for the peace of more than 60 years to this day.
Otherwise, there would not have been such a smooth rise for China.
The backwardness at the beginning of our republic
is unimaginable for the young people today.
After going through over a century of turmoil and wars,
China became "poor and blank" from
one of the richest countries in the world.
Chairman Mao had a paragraph describing China at that time.
He said, "What can we make now?"
"We can make tables, chairs, tea bowls, teapots, grains, flour, and paper."
"But we cannot even make one car, one airplane, one tank, or one tractor."
This was the real situation of China at that time.
After that we began a national rejuvenation
characterized by industrial construction,
but this process was not smooth.
When we look back at the past thirty years,
from 1949 to Reform and Opening in 1978,
we determined to give priority to industrial development, especially heavy industry.
We learnt from the Korean War that we would be bullied without steel.
Meanwhile we also did a lot in social undertakings
such as women's liberation, land reform,
universal education, universal medical care and so on.
We constructed the basic political system
and formed a relatively complete industrial system,
national defense system and technology system.
Looking back, these laid crucial foundations for China's rise.
"At thirty, I had planted my feet firm upon the ground." [by Confucius]
The achievement we attained in the first 30 years was the basis
of the Reform and Opening and
the rise of our country in the following 40 years.
But we paid a heavy price for the detour we took in political revolution.
We owed a lot to people's livelihoods and
their living standards remained very low.
The majority Chinese people were struggling around the poverty threshold
according to the international standard in 1978.
In the measurement of GDP per capita,
China's per capita GDP at that time was
lower than most African countries.
Shanghai was one of China's most prosperous cities,
but the living area per capita of most
families was under 4 square meters.
I went to Bangkok, the capital of Thailand
in 1983 for the first time.
I believe it was at least 20 years ahead of Shanghai.
Even when I went to Africa in 1984 and 1985, to the
capital of Zimbabwe and the capital of Côte d'Ivoire,
I believe these two cities were more developed than Beijing.
That was how I truly felt.
Over the forty years of Reform and Opening,
we have found our own way of success,
which could be described as "At forty,
we no longer suffered from perplexities" [by Confucius].
As President Xi said, "We took a giant leap from
standing up, to getting rich, and to getting strong".
I have been to more than one hundred countries
and I like to compare China's rise with other countries.
I divided all the countries into three groups –
developing countries,
countries in economic transition,
and western countries.
This comparison will allow us to better understand the China Path, the China Mode and China's rise.
I will begin with developing countries.
What's the biggest challenge in developing countries?
Without a doubt, it is to fight poverty,
and China is the most successful developing country in this sense.
According to our own standard,
740 million Chinese people were lifted out of poverty in the past forty years.
The number will change to 850 million
by the World Bank's standard.
It means nearly eighty percent of global poverty was eliminated by China.
Some may say China now faces a huge wealth gap.
I agree,
but we need to put this into perspective through comparison with other countries.
I have said this a lot,
when you compare China with other developing countries,
you can drive twenty hours from Beijing or Shanghai,
to Mohe in Heilongjiang, or to Hainan, or Guangzhou, or Chongqing,
as long as you don't drive into the sea.
If you record the poverty you see,
it would be less than what you see in a two-hour drive in a typical developing country like India.
Their situation is much worse than ours.
They have people in absolute poverty.
Because we are a socialist country,
and our farmers own land and houses after the land reform.
Things are completely different here.
I have a good friend from Indonesia
who studies [community] development.
His Chinese hosts kept telling him,
"You shouldn't only focus on Beijing and Shanghai.
You should go to the poverty-stricken places such as Guizhou Province".
So, he really went to Guizhou himself
and found that the poverty was different from Indonesia-
Guizhou was much more developed.
For example, he visited a poor family.
They had a house, farmland,
and the families in poverty he visited had three dishes and a soup for a meal.
He said poor people in Indonesia didn't have a house.
Their food was awful and insufficient.
So our poverty excludes the basic living needs.
I remember when I was in Europe in 2010,
a debris flow struck Zhouqu, Gansu Province.
What drew my attention was that
many of the fallen houses were equipped with air conditioners.
For all the developing countries I visited,
air conditioner was a luxury.
First of all, the municipal electricity supply must be able to meet the demand,
which was impossible in a country like India.
But in a city of China like Zhouqu, air conditioner had been popularized in 2010.
I believe we need higher standards and stricter requirements on our work.
However, comparing with the countries that I have been to,
we have actually done a much better job.
The living standard of people in poverty has also improved a lot than forty years ago.
According to our poverty standard now,
there are about thirty million people in poverty as of this year.
By the end of 2020, we are going to pull these people out of poverty
and completely eliminate extreme poverty.
I think the miracle of eliminating extreme poverty made by China
will be recorded on the history of human civilization.
Secondly, we compare China with countries in economic transition.
This is a concept I don't prefer.
It refers to socialist countries and former socialist countries
transitioning from planned economy to market economy, a definition made by the World Bank.
But at the moment, I haven't found a better expression of the idea.
So, I will go with this definition.
It makes me sigh comparing with these countries.
I remember when the Soviet Union and Eastern Europe collapsed about 27 years ago,
the west was cheering,
"The great western democracy has arrived in the Iron Curtain."
They thought Eastern Europe and Soviet Union
was heading towards a bright future.
But years later, we can compare China with these countries in economic transition.
They are incomparable .
Sometimes I say the gap between China and these countries is "as wide as between heaven and earth"
When the Soviet Union collapsed,
Russia's economy was larger than China.
But like I mentioned, Russia's economy is about the same size as Guangdong Province today.
Our national foreign exchange reserve is now more than US$ 3 trillion.
The number was very small
when I was an interpreter for the national leaders in the 1980s.
It is like an economic sector that has grown out of nothing.
Our foreign exchange reserves alone exceed
the combined GDP of Russia and the whole of Eastern and Central Europe today.
This enormous change indicates in a way
that our model is more successful than theirs.
The last comparison is between China and western countries.
There are still some people in China kowtowing to the United States.
So, let's compare China with America.
Taking average life expectancy as an example here,
the average life expectancy of Shanghai is 83 years, 4 years longer than New York.
Our Infant mortality rate is lower than New York.
Our social security level is more than 10 times higher than New York.
When I was in New York in October,
the mayor of New York City announced,
“Good news!
In the past 25 years, this is the first time
we haven’t had a single shooting for three consecutive days over a weekend.”
That means a shooting happened on the fourth day.
You can imagine their social security level.
I have always stressed that
we should learn from the strengths of all the other countries,
including America,
but we must stay clear-headed about the problems of western countries.
We have broader horizons than the western countries.
I often say that China has its own developed regions.
The population in these regions is over 400 million, more than America's population.
I often use median household net worth as a measure of household wealth.
According to the U.S. Federal Reserve in 2010
and a study following the same standards in the same year
by Southwestern University of Finance and Economics,
China's median urban household net worth is about US$ 10,000 lower than America.
This number is $ 66,300 for China and $ 77,300 for America,
about more than 500 thousand yuan.
But if you compare America to China's developed regions,
America would be a disadvantaged social class in cities like Shanghai,
because the net worth includes the worth of people's house properties.
This is a dramatic change in my opinion.
We couldn't imagine to be comparable with America forty years ago,
but now we are confident to be their match.
Some may say that I only compared China's urban population with America's
and didn't take our rural population into account.
Yes, I did that on purpose.
This report didn't consider the farmers' land
and they have the right of use and management of their land.
I don't think it's a fair comparison
if it doesn't include the land ownership for various reasons.
I think the report should estimate the value of the land even with a hypothetical price.
Now land prices are pretty high, aren't they?
Farmers prefer rural Hukou [household registration] rather than a Shanghai Hukou,
because so much property accrues to a rural Hukou
If we believe such indicators show the progress in economy, wealth, and material,
I can also look at other indicators to verify our progress in other aspects.
I often refer to American Pew Research Center
European Ipsos’s polls on China
and other major countries for the past 10 years or more.
For example, there was a simple question in the 2016 Ipsos poll:
do you think your country is on the right path?
90% of Chinese gave positive answers
while only 11% of French did so.
Thus, we can understand why the "yellow vest" protest happened in France.
In November 2017, I debated Bernard-Henri Lévy, an anti-China philosopher in France,
who criticized human rights in China.
Actually, he is the person who pushed France and western countries to invade Libya by force,
to overthrow governments, and to support color revolutions like the Arab Spring.
And I quoted this poll data. I said, look,
only 11% of French think France is on the right path,
while the other 80% are not satisfied.
Have you ever considered how much of the dissatisfaction resulted from human rights issues?
I lived in France and I know France has many human rights issues, doesn’t it?
So, I said “Mind your own business”.
Then he mentioned human rights in Xinjiang.
I said that you have already messed up Libya,
Syria,
and Iraq.
Now you want to mess up Xinjiang as well?
No way! We won’t let it happen!
By the way, China and the world are now connected through globalization.
For example, if you want to know whether the "yellow vest" movement will continue in France and Europe,
you don’t even need to be in France.
Just go to Yiwu Small Commodity Market
and ask the vendors about the sales of vests.
The sales would indicate whether the movement will continue.
I suppose for the 2020 U.S. presidential election,
you'll probably know who will win
by seeing which party's hats sell the best.
Anyway, it is a new index system,
through which the Chinese people can see the world more humorously.
Some people in the world have always been questioning China.
For example, some say that
[the economy of] China has only grown in quantity but not in quality.
In fact, China's qualitative growth is also fast,
including our great progress in scientific research and innovations.
Frankly speaking, China is the country with the fastest progress in the world.
While the rise of Huawei I just mentioned is the epitome.
I can give some other examples,
such as China's rail transportation
represented by high-speed trains, China’s communication equipment,
smartphones, and power grids.
China has the world 's best UHV, smart grid technologies,
and 5G technologies with independent property rights,
which panic America a lot.
We are more or less ahead in many aspects:
China's hydropower, thermal power, and fourth-generation nuclear power.
Almost all the world's largest engineering projects are in China,
including high-speed rails,
Hong Kong-Zhuhai-Macao Bridge,
stealth fighters, large transport aircraft,
quantum communication, high-performance computers,
BeiDou Navigation Satellite System, shale gas development, etc.
It can be said that China is leading the world in these fields.
My conclusion is simple.
That is, after 70 years of endeavor and exploration,
Chinese people have found their way to success.
We call it “socialism with Chinese characteristics”
and I sometimes call it the China Model.
We can say that
China is the first socialist country in human history
that has become the world's largest economy
according to the purchasing power parity,
created the world's largest middle class,
and exported the most tourists to the world.
China also has the largest and fastest-growing consumers’ market,
the world's largest foreign exchange reserves,
and is the world's largest trader of goods.
China has basically achieved universal pension plan and health care.
Although there are inequalities in these systems,
at least the United States has not achieved this.
Therefore, no matter how many problems we still have today,
we must first affirm our hard-earned achievements
and then enhance our work on this basis.
Although this model is still being improved,
China can stand up to international comparisons,
even with our current status.
I believe that as long as we continue to move forward along our explored “road to success”,
our future will be even brighter!
That's my speech for today, thank you.
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
Thank you, Professor Zhang, for your wonderful speech.
As you mentioned in the speech,
it's now time for the Chinese people to be confident.
Many people say that
we should have more confidence in China for China’s great progress,
but they also wonder to what extent this confidence is appropriate.
For example, some say that China is good at net sports,
but are somehow disadvantaged in the combat sports.
In country-to-country competitions,
we may have “close combats” with another country.
Can we do well in such competitions?
China Now
Today, China’s interests encompass the entire world.
If you dare not stand up and defend your own interests,
who will stand up for you?
In fact, Chinese people don't agree with this logic.
In the press both domestic and abroad,
we see anxiety and doubt.
But if they still choose not to believe us, so what?
China Now with Zhang Weiwei
We must be confident, but not conceited.
If you have true confidence about China’s achievements in comparison with the world,
the foreigners or whoever you talk with will be impressed.
This is very natural.
I like the example you gave:
China is good at sports without person-to-person collisions,
but bad at sports like soccer.
One solution is to practice collision sports.
Another is to promote the sports we are good at in the international arena
and make them the mainstream sports, such as table tennis.
This is also what the West has done.
Western sports were originally not popular in most countries.
Recently I saw a WeChat meme
about how everyone seemed to have “Mercury Retrograde” in 2018?
Even for China, we have experienced Sino-US trade frictions
and the recent incident of Meng Wanzhou.
In the press both domestic and abroad,
we see anxiety and doubt.
How should we evaluate and respond to these?
I think what we are discussing here will help us see the bigger picture of China and the world.
Otherwise,
we would lose the strategic focus.
If you can see the bigger picture,
you will stay calm.
For example, there are discussions about private enterprises
being sluggish or performing poorly in the market.
In fact, when you look at China’s
macroeconomic system —the mixed economy model,
it includes two functioning sectors:
the government and the market;
the state-owned enterprises and the private enterprises.
In this model, the two sectors complement each other,
despite infrequent conflicts.
When the two sectors are in conflicts,
the central government basically hopes to bring them into a complementary relationship.
In the bigger picture,
although there are fluctuations [in the performance of these sectors],
they will get back on track of the China Path.
With a strategic focus, we will stay calm.
- Yes, confidence is very important.
- Right.
Professor Zhang, you talked about development and changes just now.
Yesterday, one of my college classmates who has been living abroad for years
told me that China’s progress can be perceived in the small things in our life.
One year, before he returned to China,
he told his dad in China to buy a portable charger.
His dad was like “Why don’t you just get one abroad?”
My classmate said that he didn’t know where
people would sell portable chargers in his country.
Which country was he in?
No offense, he was in France.
He said that the small changes he perceived in his life made him believe
that China had already outpaced Western countries,
at least in some aspects.
Professor Zhang published “The Chinese, You Need to Be Confident” in 2004.
As you mentioned before, there was still a lack of
confidence among the intellectual community until today,
which only appealed to a small readership.
Only a minority of us realized we should have been confident.
But now you'll find something has changed.
The confident group has grown a lot.
I have been calling on for confidence for more than twenty years, not just from now.
It can be compared with your school life,
from middle school to university.
even if you don’t get good grades,
you still can catch up if you believe in yourself.
This is also true for our country.
It is the same for Chinese students abroad.
They feel that even if they are underperforming now,
they have to outperform [the local students]
in the future. They have the spirit.
I see that our audience is very young,
and you all came with questions.
Now we will start the Q&A segment.
Professor Zhang welcomes all difficult questions.
Is everyone ready?
- Professor Zhang, I am a Kirgiz student from Xinjiang.
- Welcome.
As China's economy rises,
the traditional cultures of some ethnic minorities are negatively affected.
How can we help ethnic minorities protect their unique cultures
while continuing modernization? Thank you.
When we were in Germany last month,
a German talked about human rights issues in Xinjiang.
I asked him whether he had been to Xinjiang? He said “No”.
I said that all of the Chinese delegation here are Han people,
but all of us can sing Uyghur songs.
The Uyghur people still use their own script
and speak their own dialect.
We are at the forefront of the world in protecting minority cultures.
But I agree with you that we can do better.
Thank you very much.
For some historical reasons,
China's international political influence doesn't match
its economy's size and economic influence.
Do you think that in the next few years,
China will take the old way of gaining political influence
in a low profile while developing the economy,
or that China will be more proactively
expanding its political influence?
Thank you.
I think your question is more
related to the rise of China’s hard power;
while China's soft power seems insignificant abroad
for some historical reasons.
Some of the reasons, as you mentioned,
are that China has been immersed in developing its economy
and creating wealth but ignoring the growth of its soft power.
China's soft power can grow a little faster.
President Xi Jinping has set
"telling the stories of China" as a strategic task.
The key is to have the power to tell stories.
It is not only about spending on TV stations or websites abroad,
but also about the penetrability of our language.
Can your words be understood and accepted by others?
For example,
Western countries always divide
political systems into democracy or autocracy.
I say this is wrong.
If you want to divide the world's political systems into two categories,
there are only good governance and bad governance.
Good governance can be a Western democratic system
or a non-Western democratic system.
This is a relatively more powerful narrative
and more people are beginning to accept it.
Whether soft power or hard power, it is power.
People used to have no interest in what China said,
but now they are eager to listen.
Wherever you hold a lecture about China,
people are flocking to attend.
Proactiveness doesn't mean that we are aggressive,
but like Prof Zhang said,
tell them about China’s peaceful rise in a way they can understand.
Let's move on to the next quetion.
Yes, please.
When I heard you saying that
we should know our global position,
it reminded me that
the global hegemon is said to be changing every one hundred years.
For example, the Netherlands ruled for more than one hundred years as the "sea coachman",
and the United States has been dominant for almost
100 years owing to its manufacture industry and war profiteering.
So, will China take dominance in the next century,
and will we admit this new position?
In fact, Chinese people don't agree with this logic.
China has been ahead of the West in most periods
of its five-thousand-year history.
In the first half of the 15th century, the Ming Dynasty, Zheng He reached the waters of Indian Ocean
eighty years before Columbus discovered the new continent.
The main ship's drainage was a hundred times bigger
than the main ship of Columbus.
Different from western countries,
we didn't colonize or invade other countries.
You can see that China has different cultural genes.
Chinese culture truly advocates peace.
You have asked that question in America’s logic, that is,
there will always be a winner and a loser.
China’s logic is that two countries can play a win-win or all-win game,
but America doesn't accept this.
I often say that they will accept it
because China's development momentum can't be reversed.
Our prediction is that 30 years later,
when our young people born in the 90s and 00s
become the backbone of the society,
China's economic size measured by purchasing power parity
will be the sum of the United States and the European Union,
if the EU still exists.
At that time, it will be irrelevant to talk about
who is said to be Number One.
If the United States claims to withdraw from globalization,
frankly speaking for myself as a scholar rather than our government,
I would say "So what?"
China is still the biggest trading partner of more than 130 countries;
we can continue to go forward leading these countries.
We don’t need to care about the rankings
when China has risen.
I never look at them.
This question also made me think about
how we know the West quite well,
especially after Reform and Opening,
but in turn, the West seems to be quite unfamiliar with us,
with our culture, and with China’s political developments.
So, what should we do
if they always fail to understand China
and don’t intend to understand China?
I gave a speech at Harvard University on October 15th this year [2018].
In the Q&A segment, we also discussed this question.
I said we had been repeatedly and kindly explaining China,
but if the West still choose not to believe us, so what?
"We could leave you in darkness."
"We don't care."
Germany was frowning upon our "Belt and Road Initiative".
I told them about a decade ago,
China sincerely believed Europe was our strategic partner
and signed an agreement to develop the Galileo Plan together,
which was Europe's GPS system.
China took it very seriously and invested money in it.
But the Europeans set all the restrictions they could on China’s participation in the projects.
So, China decided to do it on our own.
Now our BeiDou system is far ahead of the Galileo system.
I told them, “Don’t make the same mistake again!"
"We don’t wait for you."
"We definitely don’t.”
We're moving forward, on a high-speed train.
We go fast.
I think their continued incomprehension
of China is their loss of soft power.
In the past six months, some Western countries had criticisms on China,
including on the Belt and Road Initiative,
but many African and Asian countries, retorted promptly that
they have their own understanding [of the initiative], and
that they have their own observations and judgments.
Yes.
The heatedly discussed Huawei incident,
to some extent, reflects the emotional stress among Chinese people.
China must keep calm and stick to its strategic plan.
Now, the Chinese government has many policies
to invigorate private small and medium-sized
enterprises [SMEs] for greater market participation.
But at the same time, there are regulatory policies,
such as deleveraging and environmental restrictions,
which are implemented to affect private SMEs much more negatively
than state-owned enterprises.
I'd like to hear your opinion on this contradiction.
China Now
Different views can be discussed and debated.
We are not at all afraid of competition.
China, be confident.
China Now with Zhang Weiwei
But at the same time, there are regulatory policies,
such as deleveraging and environmental restrictions,
which are implemented to affect private SMEs much more negatively than state-owned enterprises.
I'd like to hear your opinion on this contradiction.
I totally understand your question about this contradiction.
Recently, we did a small study in Kunshan
and we saw this contradiction as well.
This is the China model—the mixed economy model I talked about.
In terms of our macroeconomic strategy,
we hope that the private economy can complement
the state-owned economy with different functions,
and have positive interactions between the two sectors.
But in practice, there are contradictions and troubles from time to time.
President Xi Jinping answered this question in the
central government's forum for private enterprises.
In the process of deleveraging,
many local governments take the one-size-fits-all approach.
In technical terms, this is not “seeking truth from facts”.
For example, some enterprises were able to meet the environmental standards,
but the local government closed the whole
industry to save themselves some trouble.
This should be corrected.
The China model is not perfect yet.
But when we find problems, we improve the model.
This is its characteristic.
Private enterprises should also understand the big picture themselves.
President Xi has attached great importance to improving
the quality of the economy since his presidency.
This is actually a new opportunity for private enterprises.
Some private enterprises refuse to
upgrade themselves further in the value chain.
This shows challenges in the transformation of private enterprises
and the mindset of “keeping up with the times”.
- Thank you Professor Zhang.
- Thank you. Please sit down.
We are very grateful for all the questions from the audience.
They came here well-prepared with their thoughts.
I wonder if they are satisfied with today’s Q&A segment,
and whether Professor Zhang enjoyed it.
There are many episodes coming up.
They can keep asking questions next time.
Just as Professor Zhang forecasted, we will
air one episode after another in the future
to discuss China-U.S. relations,
the East-West political systems,
China's industrial revolution and so on.
We look forward to the discussions
and thank you for your participation.
Thank you for the questions again.
And thank you, Professor Zhang. I’d also like to thank our production team. Thanks, everyone.
We'll see you next time!
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组